okay let's get
started good morning everyone thank you
so much for joining us for our covid-19
pandemic travel insurance plans and best
practices webinar as you know my name is
brenn and I'm the employee benefit
specialist here at Maximus Rose and this
morning I'm joined by Jonathan from Manu
life Jonathan is an internal wholesaler
for the GTA Affinity Market thanks
Jonathan for joining us this morning
thanks for having me Bren of course of
course
right so let's get started the agenda
today we'll do an in Insurance overview
a travel insurance overview we'll also
look at the co9 global travel advisory
issued by the government of Canada we'll
look at Travel coverage through employee
benefits and look into some of the
important considerations the fine
print uh of travel insurance policies
those Infamous Clauses that are always
included in the policy we'll also hand
it over to Jonathan who will be speaking
to us about manual life's covid-19
pandemic travel insurance plan and he'll
also speak to us about credit card
travel insurance because we often have
questions about what coverage is
available through credit cards and then
we'll finish off with a Q&A session
uh important note that this presentation
is not encouraged to is not intended to
encourage non-essential travel neither
manual life nor Maximus Rose is
encouraging non-essential travel but
rather we're just presenting information
about what options are available and
what considerations to take into
account so looking at outof Country
travel right now during the
pandemic if you go to the government of
Canada's travel advisory website right
on the landing page is this big red box
that says official Global travel
advisories so there's an advisory to
avoid non-essential travel outside of
Canada until further notice so there's
no end date and also avoiding all cruise
ship travel outside of
Canada so Canadians are of course free
to travel to countries that have open
borders uh including the US which
despite having a closed land border at
the moment is allowing Canadians to fly
into the
country but it's not advised at this
time and there's a couple reasons why
travel isn't advised right now one of
them is that if you're going to another
country there's no guarantee that there
is going to be medical space available
for you in hospitals or clinics right
now there's always a preference for
giving space to Residents and there's
also if we remember back in March or
April
what happened with Canadians who were in
Peru Peru chose to close their borders
to international travel and a lot of
Canadians felt as if they were stranded
in Peru um and the government had to
organize this plane to return Canadians
and repatriate Canadians
and Under This Global travel advisory
there's no guarantee that that something
like a repatriation is available so it's
your responsibility to check the
government of travel government of
Canada's travel advisory
website and Jonathan is going to speak
about that covid-19 specific coverage um
a little bit later so we'll get some
more information on that but
specifically just briefly looking at
what travel insurance is travel
insurance provides financial protection
for unforeseen medical emergencies
accidents or
illnesses a lot of Travelers have more
than one plan so so you're often covered
under your own employee benefits plan
then you may have coverage to your
spouse you may have a credit card
insurance coverage or you may have
chosen to purchase a individual
plan but there are a few things that are
very specific to travel insurance that
would control or contribute to a a
comprehensive plan and that's of course
the outof country emergency medical
coverage being the most important that's
going to cover those unforeseen medical
expenses trip cancellation and trip
Interruption which right now at the
moment is kind of in limbo for a lot of
insurers the loss or theft of baggage
and valuables coverage which is uh
fantastic because we've all traveled and
either lost our our baggage or
experienced a type of theft or a close
encounter and 24 hour access to a
representative that speaks your language
ideally
so looking specifically at trip
cancellation
um so since March 13th many Canadians
are not eligible for trip cancellation
and trip interrup Interruption coverage
due to covid-19 specifically if you
choose to book a trip after this travel
advisory which is still in effect or if
you purchase trip cancellation and trip
Interruption insurance right now you may
not actually have that coverage if it's
uh due to covid-19 and there's
unexpected expenses that may arise uh
causing you to have your trip
interrupted or extended Etc so it's very
specific very important that you
understand your specific policy that
you've
purchased going into covid-19 and
employee benefits coverage specifically
so travel insurance is a great feature
of your employee benefits plan but it's
really really important that you
understand the fine print of your
policy the type of coverage varies by
the carrier we have a collection of
people here with many different carriers
so every carrier has their
own own specificity and own rules of how
they're dealing with this covid-19 so if
you do want an update of how your
carrier is responding to covid-19 and
travel feel free to email me I'll
definitely send you an update I have
them for all of the
carriers but when the advisory was first
issued in March a lot of insurers had
actually stopped coverage for covid-19
related medical emergencies abroad and
now several insurers have resumed
offering coverage for covid-19 expenses
along with or on top of regular travel
insurance plans but not all contracts
have the same policy wording so it's
very important that you understand
what's specific to your
policy because often eligibility is
based on if there is that government
travel advisory to a region or not which
is why a lot of travel insurance does
not cover travel to a a country that's
in the middle of a a war or there's an
issue happening internally so your
coverage is often not extended to going
to those
places uh similar to
covid-19 covid-19 is no longer an
unforeseen emergency situation it's
foreseen and for warn so if you get sick
to covid-19 some carriers are not
covering uh through medical uh employee
benefits but on the flip side if you are
abroad and you
fall you may be covered because this was
an unforeseen accident it was not due to
covid-19 so again you have to look at
what is the contractual def definition
of an emergency in your policy write
down exactly what is covered and which
circumstances are covered under your
policy find out if family members are
covered if there are any exemptions or
limitations and find out if you have a
deductible for example and if you can
afford to pay that duct
deductible and also um if you see
discrepancies or don't feel that your
coverage is enough you can always do a
top up with an individual
plan speaking specifically to these
airlines that are now offering uh
coverage for covid-19 alongside their
travel packages so Air Canada WestJet
Sunwing flight center they're all
offering covid-19 medical coverage for
free so obviously they're trying to
entice people to travel and to make up
some of those losses that they've
incurred through the year
please understand that one the coverage
for covid-19 could be quite low so if
you are traveling to the US you may not
be covered for all the medical expenses
that are incurred because of obviously
the high prices for medical
care so make sure you understand how
much you're covered for and you you're
aware that you may have to pay on top
for those medical
expenses so I just pulled from uh one of
the insurers online what they're saying
about travel insurance right now and
trip Interruption
coverage
so what if I have travel medical
insurance and I'm traveling to countries
affected by covid-19 your Certificate of
Insurance has specific exclusions
related to emergency travel medical
insurance if you are traveling to a
country or region the Canadians have
been instructed to avoid all
non-essential travel to that's every
country in the world that means that
while this non-essential travel advisory
remains in place you will not be covered
for any claim if you contract the Corona
virus
so if you read between the lines you're
not covered for covid-19 but you're
covered possibly for other emergency
travel issues that
arise uh same with trip
cancellation given the official Global
travel advisory Canadians have been
instructed to avoid all non-essential
travel travel this means that you are
not eligible for trip cancellation
coverage if you book a trip or purchase
a trip again after this non-essential
travel
advisory So speaking specifically again
to um the fine print of your policy
regardless of where you are going your
condition may not be covered if you are
sick before you leave so there are a
couple Clauses that are in effect on
travel insurance policies one of them
being the pre-existing condition Clause
meaning if you leave and you are sick
you may not be covered because you are
aware that you are sick um and there's
also a stability Clause meaning that um
a lot of insurers require that if you
have a pre-existing medical condition it
must be stable for a specific period of
time prior to applying for insurance
it's usually 90 100 20 or 180 days
depending on the policy conditions that
have not been stable for the requested
period are excluded from
coverage and again the pre-existing
condition Clause you cannot leave Canada
with covid-19 if you have covid-19 or if
you become unexpectedly ill on the day
of your trip please consider or please
cancel your trip because you will not be
covered and again after reading the fine
print take into consideration medical
facilities may not be open during this
time or they'll be open but there may
not be spaced they may be overwhelmed
often there's a preference for giving
beds to
Residents understand your coverage
maximums and you must quarantine for 14
days upon re-entry into
Canada check how long you're covered for
is it two weeks or is it 90 days check
the age that you're covered until are
you does your coverage end at age 65 and
will you be away during that time when
it's your birthday check if only
essential business travel is covered
because there are some insurers that are
only traveling essential business
coverage right
now only covering essential business
travel excuse me um and check if you
have to register your trip with the
government of Canada so there's a lot
that you have to look into make sure
that you know what your insurance
carrier is requesting and what the fine
of your
policy okay so if you are concerned that
your group insurance policy doesn't
cover your needs you can always buy
additional coverage tailored to suit
your situation so I'm going to pass it
over now to Jonathan and he's going to
speak to us about covid-19 um and Manu
life
offering awesome thank you so much Bren
H thank you so much for the detailed
information and uh also thank you for
giving me this amazing opportunity for
me to come on to this webinar and answer
some questions around what manual life
has to offer on the individual travel
insurance side of the business uh so
like Bren said I'm my name is Jonathan
and I am the GTA Affinity wholesal here
at manual life and uh one of our main
product is the travel insurance um and
right now ladies and gentlemen we are at
War right now there is a global pandemic
going on and everyone is battling that
to the best of our efforts therefore it
is very important for everyone to have
the weapons that you need in order to
protect yourself against the uh these
unforeseen emergency medical situations
uh so that you don't bankrupt your
wallet um in in the event that you
contract this uh well spread virus okay
so we I'm just going to start off with
some product
highlights in regards to what our
individual travel insurance covers at
the moment so we now have a covid-19
pandemic travel plan so if you do need
to travel to the states or anywhere
outside of Canada uh we do have a plan
that covers your needs um to protect
yourself against
covid-19 so this product can be purchase
as a standalone uh which means that if
you don't have any
coverages you can just purchase this one
and that will cover your emergency
medical needs or like Brin mentioned uh
if you do have Group Insurance already
uh if you want to top up your existing
coverage by adding more coverage limits
and extend the duration of the trip you
can also purchase this product as
well there are two main components to
this covid-19 coverage the first
component is 5 million emergency medical
coverage for conditions unrelated to
co9 so these coverage items includes
events such as physical injuries
illnesses unrelated to
covid-19 uh or uh for example car
accidents these physical events that's
not related to any
illnesses okay and then separately we
also have 1 million
coverage for expenses related to
covid-19 okay so that's on top of the $5
million coverage for nonco 19 coverage
so this $1 million coverage will cover
you for Hospital expenses if you are put
on a ventilator at the hospital this
will also cover that so for basically
treatments related to covid-19 and the
hospital expenses related to that as
well that will fall under the $1 million
coverage
other than emergency medical coverage we
also have trip into Russian benefits as
well so for example if there are
unexpected quarantine situations we will
cover the meals and hotel expenses due
to this unexpected
quarantine we also cover expenses
related to government advisory
escalations okay if the covid-19
situation worsens at the destination
country we will pay for the unexpected
expenses and a fly back to Canada okay
other than that we also have automatic
extensions uh in the event that your
return to Canada is delayed beyond your
control due to hospitalizations or
quarantine delays okay so these are the
main coverage highlights under our
individual
coverage so for me personally I'm always
curious about what other people are
thinking about uh in terms of traveling
outside of Canada during this pandemic
okay so I here I have some interesting
stats that I want to share with
everybody based on the survey that was
conducted in September 2020 more than
half of the Canadians say that they're
considering taking a vacation within the
next year or
so and the popular destinations are the
tropical destinations South America
Florida the Caribbeans etc
etc and specifically for Canadians uh
there was a National Post article saying
that Canada's Die Hard snowbirds plan to
spend the winter in the US no matter
what
happens okay and an estimated 300,000 to
375,000
snowbirds are thinking about traveling
this
year in terms of the destinations in
us uh the popular destination includes
Florida Arizona and
California okay so the PE uh so the
places down south where it's warm and
where it's nice that's where the snowb
burst wants to
go and then just shifting the stats to
the ex expenses related to covid-19 so
in the states the average cost of the
Intensive Care Unit in the US is $99,000
a day that's US Dollars by the way
and the average estimated cost of a
ventilator using a ventilator in the US
is roughly 208 sorry $2,800 a day for
the use of the ventilator okay so
everybody can see that you know there is
a huge demand for travel right
now despite the fact that it's a
pandemic going on people still want to
get get outside of Canada and go
somewhere warm and uh just in terms of
that the cost of if cont if you do
contract the covid-19 virus the costes
are very very high so therefore it is
important to get the coverage you need
prior to leaving for the
tra so like BR mentioned uh Group
Insurance does have um coverages for
covid-19 as well right so just I will
take a couple minutes to um compare and
contrast the differences between Group
insurance and individual insurance so in
terms of emergency medical coverage with
manual life it is pretty standard for
both areas so we will cover Hospital
expenses medications and transportation
expenses such as air ambulance or ground
ambulance okay so for these areas it is
pretty uh pretty similar among these two
coverages and in terms of trip
Interruption coverage so this is for if
something happens at the destination
something that happens that will
interrupt your trip
so if you are uh experiencing an
emergency medical situation which you're
forced to quarantine groupy insurance
and individual insurance will both cover
it however the the differences are what
if you are not experiencing emergency
medical situation such as you don't have
covid-19 personally but you're forced to
quarantine anyways because let's just
say your family gets covid-19 right in
this situation uh Group Insurance may
not cover that for the unexpected cost
for hotels and
meals however individual insurance will
cover that okay on top of that we also
have coverage for flights and unexpected
expenses to return back to Canada if
there is a travel advisory escalation
right so right now let's take the US for
example the us right now have a level
three Trav advisory which says avoid all
nonessential
travel but if you're in the US and then
the co cases skyrockets and the Canadian
government decides to escalate that
travel advisory to the highest possible
advisory level which is avoid all
travel in that event if you decide to
come back to Canada we will cover the
oneway flight back here okay so that's
included your trip into option coverages
well in terms of trip cancellation
coverage um like brain mentioned earlier
there are restrictions around that
because of the fact that since March
manual life has declared coron uh
covid-19 as a known event from a
insurance company's perspective so
therefore for trips booked after
March if the cancellation reason is due
to covid-19 we will not cover the refund
of of the coverages that's normally
provided under that
okay with that being said the
cancellation is exclusion is only
restricted to
covid-19 so therefore if you do have
tripping uh trip cancellation coverage
but the reason of the cancellation is
not due to covid-19 that will still be
covered and then lastly both plans have
automatic extensions which is in the
sense that
if you are hospitalized on the date of
the policy expiry we will automatically
extend the coverage for ex number of
days until you are fully recovered or if
the emergency is stabilized and you are
well enough to return back to Canada for
continued
treatments and other cover events
includes um unexpected quarantine if
you're not in a hospital but you have to
quarantine until 14 until the 14 day
period is up to return back to Canada we
will also extend the policy with free of
charge and then lastly we also cover
carrier delays as
well so it is a very common question
that that that are being asked that is
credit card coverage really enough right
so a lot of people do not purchase
individual insurance or they don't think
that they need Group Travel Insurance
because they think they're credit card
cover is enough so I'll take a couple
minutes
to clear sorry compare and contrast what
the limitations are for credit card
coverage comparing to supplementary
insurance coverage with group or
individual the first thing I want to
discuss about is pre-existing
conditions so pre-existing conditions
means uh means health conditions prior
to the start of your trip some common
examples would be blood pressure
diabetes or heart
conditions so for credit card coverage
if you have these conditions prior to
the start of your
trip and an emergency happens while
you're on the trip that is triggered by
the these pre-existing
conditions the credit card company may
not cover
that there are many credit card
companies have the limitation built into
their coverage saying that we do not
cover PES and
conditions however on the flip side of
the coin individual insurance and Group
Insurance does cover emergencies arising
from stabilized preising conditions so
it's very very important to check the
fine prints of the credit card coverage
that you
have second thing tripping to option and
cancellation
coverage for most credit card companies
they set a limit in terms of how much
they will cover for triping option and
trip cancellation coverage and many
situations the coverages provided by
them is not is not as nearly as enough
as what you would
need on the individual side for example
our trip into option and cancellation
coverage can be
set that's
customized to What
specifically well sorry what amount
specifically you have spent on the trip
right so therefore with individual
insurance within supplementary Insurance
you will get the coverage need without
spending most of the money out of the
pocket in the event of interruption and
cancellation next item we have coverage
limitations so for credit card companies
they set limits on coverages such as
medications Hospital treatments etc
etc for example for daily
medications the credit card companies
tend to set a a a amount on the number
of days to cover the medications for for
example seven days 14
days however however with individual or
group travel insurance we don't have
limits like that okay so for for example
hospitalization we cover the
hospitalization hospitalization expenses
excuse me uh up until the point where
you're stabilized or up to the policy
limit which can be 5 million or 10
million there's really no number of days
amount set in the coverages okay so on
the group Insurance side and individual
side the coverages are more
comprehensive in that
case lastly Travel
Assistance if you're not if you're not
feeling well on the trip you have to see
a doctor and you want to talk to someone
about which hospital is the nearest
to you would have to call A Travel
Assistance Center uh to get assistance
from them in order to uh to see what the
next steps are credit card companies do
not have the best service in that regard
okay some companies don't even have
24-hour um Travel
Assistance okay however with group
benefits and individual travel insurance
benefits we have 24 our assistance
centers which are very responsive and
very very helpful
and uh our Travel sance Centers will let
the client know exactly where to go for
the treatments and how the claims
reimbursement process
works so in a nutshell credit card
companies they are not in the business
to do travel insurance the travel
insurance is offered by them as a perk
to their clients however they're not
catered for this special service so
therefore it is very important for
everybody to check the fine prints of
your credit card coverage prior to
leaving for the trip and if you don't
think the coverage is enough you should
speak to an advisor and then look into
the options of getting a private
traveling Insurance
P oh back to you Bren thanks so much
Jonathan it was so thorough and
comprehensive so now we open up the
floor to anyone who may have a question
about travel and covid-19 there is a
chat box as you can send a message
through the chat or alternatively if
you're joining us by phone you can send
an email um b r y
nnb Maximus rose.com that's on the
screen mxi m s RLS
e.com we'll just give
a few moments see if any questions come
in and just a note if you're looking to
purchase one of these individual
policies through manual life Maximus
Rose also provides individual coverage
not just group benefits so please feel
free to reach out to uh either your um
benefits consultant or to me and I'll
help out with directing you to the
policies oops
[Music]
okay I don't see any questions coming in
I can give it another 30 seconds or so
um absolutely if you have any further
questions you can also just send an
email and we can answer afterwards uh
again that's BR r y nnb maximus.com
sorry I should have put it on the screen
but I completely
forgot thank you Celeste
okay well with that then I guess
Jonathan we should sign off
and Say
Goodbye yeah I just want to say thanks
to everybody uh for your time this
morning um if you have any questions
like Brin said uh feel free to reach out
to your advisors and uh yeah we will
help you out and make sure you have the
coverage you need prior to your
trip aome thanks Jonathan it was a
pleasure to have you and have you
explain everything so well and uh we'll
be in touch awesome all right thank you
so much ben thanks everybody have a good
day